Guide to the Collection of Bookplates by Stephen Gooden
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of bookplates by Stephen Gooden
1923-1966
BKP 48
Yale University Arts Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
The collection contains bookplates designed by Stephen Gooden (1892-1955). It also includes process materials—e.g., original sketches, trial proofs, and engraved plates—as well as correspondence and ephemera.
Gooden, Stephen, 1892-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011, it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Stephen Frederick Gooden (1892-1955) was an English engraver, illustrator, and woodcutter. He attended Rugby and the Slade School of Art, served in World War I, and then settled in London. Gooden mastered copperplate engraving, producing book illustrations, banknotes, and numerous bookplates—including several designs for the Royal Family. Although his career was brief, Gooden was a member of the Royal Academy and appointed a Commander of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (C.B.E.).
Reference: Dodgson, Campbell. An Iconography of the Engravings of Stephen Gooden. London: E. Mathews ltd., 1944.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains bookplates designed by Stephen Gooden (1892-1955). It also includes process materials—e.g., original sketches, trial proofs, and engraved plates—as well as correspondence and ephemera.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Bookplates, 1923-1953. II. Process Materials, 1927-1938. III. Correspondence and Ephemera, 1941-1966.
Bookplates, English; Bookplates; Printing plates; Gooden, Stephen, 1892-1955
- Bookplates, 1923-1953; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - J. N. Hart, 1923; 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Joseph Hugh Leycester, 1924; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Walden Book Shop, 1924; 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - G. F. & A. E. Waley, 1924; 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - S. L. Courtauld, 1925; 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Katharine Cromer, 1925; 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mona Gooden, 1926; 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Geoffrey Keynes, 1926; 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dorothy Moulton Mayer, 1926; 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mary Thynne, 1926; 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Harold Hartley, 1927; 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bertine Entwistle Sutton, 1927; 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes an original preliminary sketch and two final plates (one signed).
  - Antoinette Brett, 1928; 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Margaret Griselda Wedderburn, 1928; 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Edward and Cicely Hutchinson, 1929; 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - George Courtauld, 1931; 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes an original pencil drawing and a first-state print.
  - Imperial Defence College Library, 1932; 6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes versions of the plate before and after lettering.
  - Lakeside Press Library, 1932-1933; 3 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - John Raymond Danson, 1934; 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - George Harrap, 1935; 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Liverpool Medical Institution Library, 1936; 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - George Senter, 1936; 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Royal Library, Windsor Castle [Dodgson #152], 1937; 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes a first-state print.
  - Royal Library, Windsor Castle [Dodgson #153], 1937; 3 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes examples of both the Edward VIII and the George VI cyphers.
  - Royal Library, Windsor Castle [Dodgson #154], 1937; 3 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lord Harlech (William George Arthur IVth Baron Harlech), 1938; 3 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Hertfordshire Art Society, 1938; 1 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ethel Luce-Clausen, 1940; 2 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Leslie Wall, 1940; 2 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Ashwell County Primary School, 1942; 51 items (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Elizabeth R., 1942; 2 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Includes two different designs, neither of which are in Dodgson.
  - City of Liverpool Public Libraries, 1944; 10 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Includes three different designs.
  - Institute of Mechanical Engineering, 1947; 2 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Derek Spence, 1947; 1 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Royal College of Surgeons of England, 1951 1953; 4 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Central African Archives Library, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Elizabeth, undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Lord Fairhaven (Urban Huttleston Rogers), undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Margaret, undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Process Materials, 1927-1938; Series II
  This series contains the engraved copperplates for several of Gooden's ex-libris designs.
  - Harold Hartley and George Courtauld, 1927 1931; 2 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Hertfordshire Art Society and Elise Fitton, 1938 undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Correspondence and Ephemera, 1941-1966; Series III
  This series contains various correspondence and ephemera related to Gooden and his ex-libris designs.
  - Correspondence and Ephemera, 1951-1966 undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Includes correspondence with collectors and dealers, catalogs and checklists, receipts, and brochures from an exhibition of Stephen Gooden engravings in the Hornby Art Library, Liverpool, July 13-September 29, 1951.
  - Catalogues, &c., 1941 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Includes Vol. 28, No. 4 (December 1941) of The Print Collector's Quarterly.
  - Oversize, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Includes mats and signage from Yale University Library exhibition of "Engraved Bookplates by Stephen Gooden."